=== CHAIRPERSON (PDF 45-47, PRINTED 43-45) ===
Dear Stakeholders,
The global economy continued to 
be strongly adaptive in 2025, amidst 
shifting geopolitical trends and US 
policy shocks.  International trade 
remained relatively robust, supported 
by stabilising trade tensions towards the 
third quarter, and strong private sector 
investments in advanced technologies, 
particularly Artificial Intelligence. Against 
this backdrop of global recovery and 
sustained domestic political stability, 
Sri Lanka too recorded encouraging 
progress during the year. Economic 
growth was supported by declining 
interest rates and a period of deflation 
that prevailed until around August. The 
most significant distraction to sustained 
growth was Cyclone Ditwah, at the end 
of November 2025, which temporarily 
disrupted economic activity across 
the entire country. However, the swift 
recovery once again demonstrated the 
remarkable resilience of the Sri Lankan 
people. Overall, this stable environment 
proved conducive for the banking 
sector, as stronger demand for credit 
and financial services boosted banking 
industry expansion.
Your Bank was well prepared to harness 
the emerging opportunities of 2025. I am 
therefore pleased to convey the good 
news that SDB bank concluded 2025 with 
improved financial performance, while 
further strengthening the foundation for 
sustainable future growth.
OUR PERFORMANCE IN A 
NUTSHELL
Responding to emerging economic 
opportunities, SDB bank recorded 
improved financial results across all 
key business segments in the financial 
year 2025. The Bank achieved a Profit 
Before Tax of LKR 800.17 Mn, reflecting 
an increase of 16.93% compared to 
2024. This performance was supported 
by expansion across our core portfolios, 
while also improving asset quality, with 
Impaired Loans (Stage 03) to total loans 
declining from 6.93% to 5.36% as of 
December 31, 2025.
While focusing on growth and profitability, 
the Bank remained committed to 
supporting segments that continued to 
experience the protracted effects of the 
economic crisis. During the year, we 
provided relief measures, including tenor 
reductions and interest concessions, to 
assist small businesses and individuals in 
their recovery journey.
We also maintained our business 
philosophy of inclusivity and diversity, 
ensuring that our business model 
is closely aligned with the countryÆs 
development priorities, through our 
strong focus on SMEs and women 
entrepreneurs. In 2025, the SME portfolio 
grew by 45.41% in keeping with the 
bankÆs priority of supporting the financial 
needs of the sector. WeÆre proud to report 
that at year-end 2025, women accounted 
for 43% of our total clientele.
43
Integrated Annual Report 2025 | SANASA Development Bank PLC 
Responding to emerging economic opportunities, 
SDB bank recorded improved financial results 
across all key business segments in the financial 
year 2025. The Bank achieved a Profit Before 
Tax of LKR 800.17 Mn, reflecting an increase 
of 16.93% compared to 2024. This performance 
was supported by expansion across our core 
portfolios, while also improving asset quality, with 
Impaired Loans (Stage 03) to total loans declining 
from 6.93% to 5.36% as of December 31, 2025.
LKR 800.17 Mn
Profit Before Tax (+16.93% YoY)
Driven by portfolio expansion and strategic 
market positioning.

Co-operatives form another significant 
client segment of our bank, given our 
history of being established by the 
Sanasa Co-operative movement. The 
strong relationships with co-operatives 
have led to the bankÆs close ties with 
communities across the country. By 
channelling finance and advisory 
services to these communities, we are 
helping stimulate economic activity at 
the grassroots. Through our focus on 
agriculture and value-chain financing, 
we are also linking these enterprises 
with broader markets, thereby fostering 
sustainable economic ecosystems.
In 2025, we continued to strengthen 
the partnership with co-operatives 
by providing technical support and 
financial literacy education, digital 
access to societies across the country 
and designating a priority counter at our 
branches, in recognition of their loyalty 
to the bank. Through its membership, 
the co-operative network also indirectly 
connects the bank to a large group of 
women entrepreneurs. We continue to 
develop new ways of engaging with the 
island-wide network of cooperatives by 
leveraging digital solutions. We are of 
the view that the next generation of youth 
leaders and membership of co-operatives 
will be quick to adopt digital solutions, 
indicating a new era of possibilities. 
In addition, we are extending our SME 
facilities to cooperative-linked enterprises 
that are ready to upscale. This includes 
the full range of financial, advisory, and 
digital banking services to modernise 
and integrate these businesses into 
bigger markets. Through this approach, 
the Bank is gradually extending 
its influence upwards, from micro-
enterprises to medium-sized SMEs, and 
cementing long-term relationships based 
on mutual trust.
STRATEGIC PROGRESS
Under our Agri-Financing and Value 
Chain strategy, we have commenced 
engaging SMEs operating in strategic 
growth areas of Sri LankaÆs food and 
agriculture sector. To ensure our 
interventions are both practical and 
sustainable, we are also working closely 
with leading agricultural specialists. 
These efforts will also contribute towards 
enhancing national food security and 
foreign exchange earnings.
The Rural Upliftment Programme, which 
was launched in 2024, is now gaining 
traction, and we have engagements 
across the country. During the year, the 
programme grew to 3,991 beneficiaries 
onboarding over 80 entrepreneurs, with a 
large share of women and cooperatives. 
We are working on projects such as the 
Heritage Hands, which is manufacturing 
Kitul products in Deraniyagala, 
sustainable tourism in Attanagalla, 
Walawwita, and Avissawella, and 
livelihood development programmes for 
fishing communities in the area between 
Kuchchaveli and Uppuweli, to name a 
few ongoing initiatives.
Although our formal collaboration with 
USAID concluded during the year, the 
Bank remains committed to strengthening 
its climate adaptation capabilities in 
response to the growing challenges 
posed by climate change.
Digitisation remains another strategic 
priority. We continued to enhance 
operational efficiencies and streamline 
internal processes while improving 
customer accessibility through digital 
channels. Our digital onboarding 
capability allows customers to open 
accounts remotely through multilingual 
platforms, promoting financial inclusion. 
The SDB Upay application, functioning 
both as a banking app and a digital 
wallet, offers advanced features that 
place SDB Bank at the forefront of digital 
banking innovation within the sector.
ENSURING GOOD 
GOVERNANCE
I am pleased with the progress made 
during the year in strengthening the 
BankÆs governance, risk management, 
and compliance frameworks. The 
Bank successfully met all compliance 
requirements under the new Banking Act 
for the 2025 financial year and continues 
to enhance its regulatory and governance 
standards.
We also completed the planned 
improvements in portfolio underwriting 
standards and credit risk frameworks that 
were identified during the 2024 review 
of our risk models. Comprehensive 
training programmes were conducted 
to strengthen staff capabilities in these 
areas, ensuring that the Bank is well-
positioned to manage the evolving risk 
landscape. While our development-
oriented approach focuses on 
empowering SMEs and cooperative-
based enterprises, we continue to adopt 
prudent, risk-based pricing mechanisms 
to safeguard the BankÆs financial 
sustainability.
The Board, meanwhile, met regularly to 
ensure strong governance and effective 
oversight. I also take this opportunity to 
remember Mr Naveendra Sooriyarachchi, 
who passed away during the year. Mr 
Sooriyarachchi was a member of the 
SDB Bank Board from 2021 as a Non-
Executive, Non-Independent Director, 
and I extend my sincere appreciation for 
the invaluable support and guidance he 
provided throughout his tenure.
CHARTING A NEW, 
SUSTAINABLE COURSE
During the year, we worked closely 
with Rabo Partnerships to develop 
a comprehensive three-year growth 
strategy that will guide SDB BankÆs 
next phase of development from 2026 
to 2029. Representing a transformative 
shift, the bank will also work towards 
ensuring that the strategy is aligned 
with the Sustainability Standards and 
Certification Initiative (SSCI), which is an 
internationally recognised framework that 
supports financial institutions to transition 
towards sustainable business models.
A central part of the BankÆs transformation 
will be the systematic measurement of the 
impacts of all our activities, which would 
make SDB bank unique among financial 
services providers in the country. This 
transformation will be a gradual process 
unfolding over the coming years, and 
will encompass all operations and 
personnel, fundamentally reshaping how 
the Bank functions. We have already 
taken the first steps toward this vision. In 
44
SANASA Development Bank PLC | Integrated Annual Report 2025
CHAIRPERSONÆS MESSAGE

the current financial year, we refined the 
BankÆs purpose to align with this strategic 
objective and established a set of high-
impact goals linked to both the United 
Nations Sustainable Development Goals 
and Sri LankaÆs national development 
agenda. Additionally, we have begun 
integrating impact measurement into 
our projects and portfolios. We believe 
that this data-driven approach will 
enable the Bank to not only measure 
its socio-economic and environmental 
contributions, but also to focus on areas 
where it can have the greatest impact.
PLANS FOR THE FUTURE
SDB bank concluded 2025 on the cusp 
of a transformative journey, having 
completed much of the groundwork 
required to support its next phase of 
transition. As we operationalise our 
new strategy in 2026, we will remain 
attentive to global developments and 
their potential impact on the Sri Lankan 
economy.
We will also evaluate opportunities 
arising from the Central BankÆs proposed 
consolidation plans for the banking 
sector. While the Bank remains open 
to potential partnerships that could 
strengthen our asset base and earnings, 
our priority remains to preserve our 
unique identity as a development-
focused bank with a longstanding 
commitment to the SME and cooperative 
sectors.
Going forward, our short-term priorities 
will remain firmly aligned with our 
strategic roadmap, and we will continue 
to leverage innovative solutions 
to enhance our value proposition, 
while remaining alert to emerging 
opportunities.
APPRECIATION
In closing, I would like to extend my 
sincere gratitude to our shareholders for 
their continued trust, confidence, and 
support. I also wish to thank our valued 
customers who have accompanied us 
through this journey of transformation. My 
appreciation also goes to my colleagues 
on the Board, our Corporate Management 
team, and the entire SDB bank staff for 
their dedication and hard work during 
the year. I also acknowledge the valuable 
contributions of our international partners, 
whose expertise and experience continue 
to support our journey. Finally, I extend 
my thanks to our regulators, lenders, and 
all other stakeholders for their continued 
guidance and support. I am confident our 
continued collaborations will yield greater 
value for all stakeholders in the future.
Ms. Dinithi Ratnayake
Chairperson - Non-Executive, 
Independent Director
4th May 2026
Colombo, Sri Lanka
45
Integrated Annual Report 2025 | SANASA Development Bank PLC 

=== CEO (PDF 49-51, PRINTED 47-49) ===
47
Integrated Annual Report 2025 | SANASA Development Bank PLC 
I am pleased to report a year of 
transformation for SDB bank in the 
financial year 2025, marking a decisive 
turning point in the BankÆs history. 
During the 12 months under review, 
we strengthened our financial position, 
governance frameworks, digital 
capabilities, and human capital, while 
also building our environmental and 
social foundation to support sustainable 
growth over the long term.
We also  deepened our economic 
impact through the Rural Upliftment 
Programme. In 2025, SDB bank was 
privileged to contribute to Sri LankaÆs 
national economic development through 
this programme by promoting womenÆs 
entrepreneurship, advancing community-
based tourism, developing essential 
infrastructure, and enhancing financial 
literacy. By encouraging womenÆs 
entrepreneurship in cottage industries 
in the North Central, North Western, 
Central, and Sabaragamuwa provinces, 
the Bank helped break the cycle of 
poverty and empowered groups that 
were previously marginalised to become 
active contributors to national growth. 
Estate sector women, who traditionally 
had limited opportunities beyond daily 
wage labour, were supported through 
the introduction of machinery centres 
and training programmes designed to 
fit their daily routines, enabling them to 
transition into budding  entrepreneurs. In 
collaboration with the Western Province 
Tourism Board, SDB bank also promoted 
community-based tourism, honouring Sri 
LankaÆs unique culture and traditions, 
while contributing to a turning point in the 
tourism industry.
Furthermore, the Bank encouraged value-
added production using underutilised 
local resources such as jackfruit, 
pumpkin, and indigenous fruits, thereby 
strengthening national production and 
creating new economic opportunities for 
rural communities. These efforts reflect 
SDB bankÆs commitment to fulfilling its 
national responsibility as Sri LankaÆs only 
private development bank, empowering 
communities, fostering entrepreneurship, 
and promoting sustainable industries 
in order to advance inclusive economic 
development.
A YEAR OF 
TRANSFORMATION
The BankÆs financial position improved 
significantly. Following three consecutive 
years of contraction in the loan portfolio 
up to 2024, we successfully reversed 
the downward spiral in 2025. Loans to 
customers increased by 16.72 %, from 
LKR 99.73 billion as at end-December 
2024, to LKR 116.40 billion by end-
December 2025. This growth was 
achieved through credit expansion 
across all products and market segments 
of leasing, pawning, retail banking 
and business banking, with total 
disbursements of over LKR 100 billion 
during the year. We remained the bank 
of choice  to Sri LankaÆs cooperative 
sector, while also expanding our footprint 
in the SME segment. Over 25% of the 
BankÆs total lending during 2025, was 
channelled into SMEs, reflecting SDB 
bankÆs growing contribution to national 
economic recovery and inclusive growth 
during the year. Despite the expansion 
of the loan book, asset quality improved, 
with a reduction in the overall Impaired 
Loans (Stage 3) to total loan, Ratio (%) 
from 6.93 % in 2024 to 5.36%. This 
reflects disciplined credit underwriting, 
The BankÆs financial position has also continued 
to improve. Following three consecutive years 
of contraction in the loan portfolio up to 2024, 
we successfully reversed the downward spiral in 
2025. Loans to customers increased by 16.72%, 
from LKR 99.73 billion as at end-December 2024, 
to LKR 116.40 billion by end-December 2025.
LKR 116.40 BN
Loan Portfolio (+16.72% YoY)
A strategic shift reversing a three-year 
downward trend, indicating strong market 
recovery.

48
SANASA Development Bank PLC | Integrated Annual Report 2025
CHIEF EXECUTIVE OFFICERÆS REVIEW
effective portfolio monitoring, and a 
strong emphasis on maintaining quality in 
all new lending.
As a development bank, our mandate 
extends beyond short-term profitability 
to supporting long-term economic 
and social development. However, 
the combined effects of the COVID-19 
pandemic and the subsequent economic 
crisis resulted in many customers 
experiencing cash flow problems as well 
as repayment tenor extensions due to 
steep interest rate fluctuations during 
the crisis. We responded by extending 
repayment periods, providing targeted 
relief to borrowers, and continuing 
to prioritise customer rehabilitation. 
We have also focused on resolving 
legacy portfolio challenges arising 
from tenor extensions. Approximately 
12,000 customers benefited from loan 
restructurings in 2025, with many able 
to access additional financing under 
improved terms. These measures 
helped resolve nearly one-third of the 
previously troubled portfolio, representing 
substantial progress in strengthening 
the financial position of the affected 
customers as well as our balance sheet. 
We also expended approximately  LKR 
1 billion in providing relief to affected 
customers, which eroded our profitability 
for the year. Nevertheless, despite these 
interventions, we have increased our 
profitability (PBT) year-on-year, from LKR 
684 Mn in 2024 to LKR 800 Mn, which is 
a growth of 16.94%.
We also targeted higher fee income 
through avenues such as Bancassurance 
while minimising leakages through 
automation of processes as well as close 
monitoring. Our fee income accordingly 
improved from LKR 631 Mn in 2024 
to LKR 716 Mn in 2025. We intend to 
focus on this further in the coming year 
enriching our revenue mix.
MANAGING EXTERNAL 
SHOCKS
The adverse impact of Cyclone Ditwah 
on Sri LankaÆs agriculture sector posed a 
significant national challenge. However, 
as the event occurred during the tail end 
of the year, in November 2025, its impact 
on the BankÆs overall annual performance 
was minimal. While branches in 
Kaduwela, Ekala and Giriulla sustained 
significant damage, operations were 
restored within a few days, with no loss of 
customer data, or material inconvenience 
to customers.
A few community development projects 
under our Rural Upliftment Programme, 
particularly in agriculture, in areas such 
as Ududumbara, were also affected. 
These losses are not a material threat 
to the BankÆs financial stability and the 
projects will be reviewed and revived. We 
are also considering the integration of 
enhanced climate resilience strategies, 
such as smart agriculture solutions. To 
address potential food shortages due 
to the widespread destruction of crops, 
we have also initiated short-term crop 
cultivations in unaffected provinces, with 
harvests expected to reach markets by 
early 2026. A new processing centre for 
fish and seaweed will also be opened 
in Trincomalee town in 2026, which will 
improve the nutritional status of low-
income communities. Increasing the 
harvest from the ocean can also soften 
the impact of agricultural losses. In fact, 
we are involved in some highly impactful 
development projects under our Rural 
Upliftment Programme, mainly through 
our cooperative connections, and I urge 
our stakeholders to refer to the Social 
Capital chapter for details on these 
projects.
SUSTAINABLE 
TRANSFORMATION
A key aspect of our ongoing 
transformation is our new corporate 
strategy that will guide the Bank over 
the three years from 2026 to 2029. This 
strategy was formulated in collaboration 
with Rabo Partnerships, a wholly owned 
subsidiary of Rabobank, drawing on its 
deep expertise in cooperative banking, 
agriculture finance, food security 
and financial inclusion. We have also 
developed a dedicated agri-financing 
model that is aimed at positioning SDB 
bank as a key development partner for 
the countryÆs agriculture sector over 
the long term. Therefore, we are now 
equipped with a clear roadmap for 
sustained transformation and growth, 
targeting greater positive social and 
environmental impacts.
Another significant development in 
2025 was bringing previously dispersed 
departments under one roof in Colombo 
as a second head office. This will 
significantly smooth back-end processing 
as we scale up our SME, pawning, 
leasing and cooperative banking 
portfolios in the new financial year.
The digital transition remains central 
to our growth agenda. Significant 
investments have already been made 
in the previous year to modernise the 
technology infrastructure, and this 
will be the transformation base for the 
Bank as we move forward. We are 
also introducing digital solutions to 
cooperative societies and SMEs, and 
are gradually connecting them to value 
chains and markets. Our value chain 
financing initiatives have continued to 
expand during the year, creating new 
avenues for SME growth, particularly in 
the agriculture, dairy and fishing sectors, 
by linking smaller enterprises to the 
supply chains of larger corporates and 
providing more secure market access.
In parallel with these developments, 
we have invested in upskilling, talent 
acquisition and leadership development 
across the Bank to align our skill sets with 
strategic priorities and evolving market 
demands.
OUTLOOK
We have concluded 2025 with SDB bank 
well-positioned to deliver consistent 
growth over the medium term. Given the 
central role of agriculture in Sri LankaÆs 
economy, exports, livelihoods and food 
security, SDB bank will continue to 
expand its role in the countryÆs SME and 
agriculture sectors, while also expanding 
our share in other economic areas.

49
Integrated Annual Report 2025 | SANASA Development Bank PLC 
We are also cognisant of the inherent 
climate-related risks and external 
uncertainties we face, particularly when 
expanding our presence in agriculture. 
However, I am confident that SDB bankÆs 
strategy of selective sector participation, 
careful risk assessments, strengthening 
the balance sheet and enhanced 
organisational capability will enable us to 
navigate future challenges with resilience. 
Accordingly, we anticipate maintaining 
positive growth momentum in 2026.
I conclude my message by extending 
my sincere appreciation to our major 
shareholders for their continued 
confidence and support, and in particular 
to Rabo Partnerships for its contributions 
to our strategic transformation. During 
the year, FMO exited as a major 
shareholder. Nevertheless, we continue 
to maintain a close, constructive working 
relationship, with FMO remaining a 
strategic stakeholder and contributor in 
our planning process. We also expanded 
our network of partnerships, particularly 
within agriculture and rural development 
initiatives, and I gratefully acknowledge 
the support we have received from all 
of them. I am grateful for the prudent 
guidance of the Board of Directors, and 
for the dedication and commitment of 
our management team and staff, who 
have worked tirelessly to deliver the 
performance outcomes of this year. 
Above all, I thank our customers, whose 
trust and partnership remain our greatest 
strength. As we enter a new era of growth 
and opportunity, we look forward to 
continuing this journey together.
Mr. Kapila Ariyaratne
Chief Executive Officer
4th May 2026
Colombo, Sri Lanka

